<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator>
    
    
    <link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
    <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <updated>2019-11-05T08:48:15+00:00</updated>
    <id>//</id>

    
    <title type="html">spotchi.github.io</title>
    

    
    <subtitle>Musings in technology, mathematics and technology.</subtitle>
    

    

    
    
    <entry>
        
        <title type="html">Godel’s incompleteness theorems : the ultimate frontier</title>
        
        
        <link href="/2019/10/28/Godel-incompleteness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Godel's incompleteness theorems : the ultimate frontier" />
        
        <published>2019-10-28T18:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2019-10-28T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>/2019/10/28/Godel-incompleteness</id>
        <content type="html" xml:base="/2019/10/28/Godel-incompleteness/">&lt;p&gt;For millenia, people have needed a way to discover truth and knowledge about the world. The process was plagued by
sophistry and inaccuracies before Aristotle gathered his thoughts on the 
matter in a series of works named &lt;em&gt;The Organon&lt;/em&gt; (translated as “The Instrument”). Since then logic has played a central part in the development of Science and Mathematics, and is still used
informally in everyday life to decide what is right or wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logic is pretty much universal, indeed few could argue against the simple efficacy of a logical argument.
Over time, logic grew in complexity and power and is now a well-researched branch of mathematics. 
It is in fact impossible to build a mathematical argument without it.
Mathematics and logic surround us and are seen as this higher authority, though few explore the
foundations on which our knowledge is built.
Aristotle used the word “Instrument”, but these days with the rise of semi-intelligent machines it seems
more fitting to talk about logic as a mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core of logic is the formal proof. It is a sequence of sentences in formal language. In order
to determine whether the proof is valid or not, we will resort to axioms (sentences that are always
true) and inference rules (a mechanism through which a sentence can be deducted from one or more
preliminary sentence(s) known as premise(s)). We will refer to a combination of a formal language,
a set of axioms and inference rules as a formal system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what a formal proof might look like in natural language :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;em&gt;All beings are made of atoms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reggie is a being&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reggie is made of atoms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example we have taken “All beings are made of atoms” and “Reggie is a being” as axioms of
our system, and the inference rule we used is simply the fact that if a property is true for all
members of a class, then it must be true for a particular member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point here is not to argue about the truth of the axioms but more so to determine whether
a proof is valid or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-very-brief-history-of-formal-systems&quot;&gt;A very brief history of Formal Systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the end of the 19th century to the middle of the 20th century, many mathematicians worked on
formalizing Set Theory. From its inception by Georg Cantor to later work by various mathematicians
including Gottlob Frege, Bertrand Russell as well as Ernst Zermelo and Abraham Fraenkel who gave
their name to ZF(C) (Zermelo-Frankel set theory) which is still in use today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TODO : make sense&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When in the year 1900 the mathematician David Hilbert published a list of 23 problems &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#hilp&quot;&gt;(Hilbert, 1900)&lt;/a&gt;, the
notion was that with a suitable formal system, all of the statements in mathematics could either be
proved right or wrong.
 This is what we call &lt;b&gt;completeness&lt;/b&gt;. In fact, Hilbert’s 10th problem asks for
a construction of the solution for a specific class of equations, the Diophantine equations,
assuming that there had to be such an algorithm. In his second problem, he also asks for a proof of
the &lt;b&gt;consistency&lt;/b&gt; of the axioms of arithmetic, meaning whether it would be impossible to prove
a sentence in arithmetic and its opposite. The promise of finally filling the gaps in mathematics
seem to have appealed to young Kurt Gödel and he started his PhD with the intention of
contributing to Hilbert’s dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gödel-numbering-and-representability&quot;&gt;Gödel numbering and representability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This paragraph contains some mathematical notation necessary to explain how the incompleteness 
theorems came to be. If that’s not your cup of tea, go ahead and skip to the First Incompleteness Theorem section&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides consistency, there is another notion which is central to understanding Set
Theory: representability. A weakly representable set has a corresponding formula. A given integer is
in the set if and only if we can prove the formula to be true for that integer. This essentially
implies that there is a method to enumerate all elements of the set, but we might not necessarily be
able to prove that an element is not in the set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable talking about logic within the language we introduce Gödel numbering, the association of
any formula of the formal language with a natural number. This is today quite intuitive as anything
we represent in a computer is in binary code. Let us not explain exactly how this is done and assume
that there is such a mapping. More interestingly, proofs are also represented as numbers…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will define the code of a formula $A$ as $\ulcorner A \urcorner$. All the rules of logic can then 
be transposed as functions of the Gödel numbers, even the inference rules.
One key consequence of this is that we can decide whether a sequence of statements is a valid proof 
using arithmetic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that knowledge, let us go back to Set Theory.
The question of whether a number is in a set could be answered by proving that a specific formula is
true for $x$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;x \in S_A \iff F \vdash A(x) &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have introduced several notations: $F$ is the formal system that we’re working with, and
$A$ is a formula that has a value of True or False for every integer, and corresponds to the set $S_A$.
Here, $F \vdash A(x)$ indicates that it is possible to prove that $A(x)$ is True with the axioms and
inference rules of $F$.
The $\iff$ symbol indicates the provability of $A(x)$ for all elements of the set $S_a$. This
property is known as weak representability and is very important for what follows, as it establishes
a bridge between Set Theory and the formal system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now use formulas as arguments of other formulas thanks to Gödel numbering.
We could for example define the set of all provable sentences, and find a nice formula that can only
be proved to be true for the Gödel number of provable statements (formulas). We define 
provability as a formula of the language!&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F \vdash A \implies F \vdash Prov_F(\ulcorner A \urcorner)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-diagonalization-lemma&quot;&gt;The Diagonalization Lemma&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Godel numbering, we can now write equivalent formulas, but using numbers as representations of
formulas!
We can use that strange loop in mathematics to find a formula’s special “fixed point” sentence. The
diagonalization lemma tells us that for any formula $A$ we can construct a sentence $D$ such that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;F \vdash D \iff A(\ulcorner D \urcorner)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sentence’s provability is inextricably linked to $A$’s true value. If $D$ is provable, then
$A(\ulcorner D \urcorner)$ is true, and if it is false then $D$ is not provable. 
Applying this to the negation of the provability sentence described earlier yields the first
of Gödel’s incompleteness theorems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gödels-first-incompleteness-theorem&quot;&gt;Gödel’s First Incompleteness Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming $F$ is a formal system with sufficient arithmetic[^2] then we can construct a sentence $G_F$
of the language of $F$ such that $G_F$ is true but not provable. 
In other terms, we have a sentence $G_F$ that says the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;em&gt;This sentence is not provable &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could try to prove this sentence. But if we succeeded that
would mean the sentence would be provable which contradicts its very meaning. The
sentence would then be False and we cannot prove False sentences.
Is it False then? We encounter a similar problem when assuming the sentence is False, since that
would again lead us to proving a False sentence.
Seeing as we assumed that the system was consistent, that sentence is &lt;b&gt;not provable&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;not
False&lt;/b&gt; and therefore it &lt;b&gt;must be True&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gödels-second-incompleteness-theorem&quot;&gt;Gödel’s Second Incompleteness Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We &lt;b&gt;have proven&lt;/b&gt; that consistency of the system implies that the Gödel sentence is true but 
unprovable. The second theorem is about consistency and is linked to Hilbert’s second problem. It 
was noted that if a system can prove its consistency, then it must also be able to prove the Gödel
sentence $G_F$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$F$ can prove $Consistency(F)$&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gödel’s first theorem: $Consistency(F)$ implies that $G_F$ is true&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 1. and 2., we can deduce that if $F$ can prove $Consistency(F)$ then $F$ can prove $G_F$.
By contradiction, we can then conclude that consistency cannot be proven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;incompleteness-vs-decidability&quot;&gt;Incompleteness vs Decidability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the 20^th century, Alonzo Church and Alan Turing took a similar approach to prove the
undecidability of First Order Logic.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#hopcroft&quot;&gt;(Hopcroft, Motwani, &amp;amp; Ullman, 2006)&lt;/a&gt; 
A theorem that there is a mechanical way to verify is called recursive. Of course if a theorem cannot be proven, then it can hardly be verified mechanically. 
On the other hand, for a specific set, there might be a way to enumerate elements of the set, 
but there might not be a general, mechanical way to verify (prove) that a particular number belongs 
to the set. One example of such a problem is the &lt;b&gt;Halting Problem&lt;/b&gt;. It is defining the set of
programs that terminate. Of course, it is possible to build an infinity of programs that satisfy
this definition, but for a specific program it is not always possible to know if it will, like
a program that looks for integers that satisfy Fermat’s last theorems.
A system is called decidable if all of its theorems (sentences derivable in it) is decidable. 
Incompleteness of a system implies its undecidability but there are many cases where a system is
complete yet undecidable. Gödel himself showed that there are complete systems in First-Order
Logic, yet First Order Logic is undecidable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;humans-vs-mechanisms&quot;&gt;Humans vs Mechanisms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some would see these theorems as a fundamental flaw, an acknowledgement by mathematics of its own
shortcomings, though there really is nothing wrong with probing the limits of our tools for 
reasoning. Beyond Gödel’s sentence which might seem a specific edge case that should not be allowed,
there are “reasonable” cases that are not provable and even more that are not computable. So is 
there something missing in our system? Or is there any system at all with sufficient arithmetic capable of 
completeness? Based on the discussion we just had, it would seem a mathematician is capable to find 
a sentence to be true where formal systems are not able to prove them. Therefore no formal system can 
be devised that encompasses the mathematician’s knowledge or general human intelligence.
Though what struck me as I examined the consequences of the GITs, is that we actually used logic to
come to the incompleteness results. Indeed they are just another set of theorems, inferred from our
definitions of provability and notations related to Gödel numbering.
We have found that we cannot always prove the truth, yet on that journey we 
used the very system, that we are trying to understand better. The incompleteness theorems are now
just another tennet of mathematics, upon which we can expand and prove more and more theorems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incompleteness theorems are just stating a system’s limit, assuming the system to be consistent.
Any “logic machine” could verify that proof, and there is no mysterious human factor that sets us
apart from that machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mathematical introspection had a major influence in the development of computer
science. In fact formal systems were a central of artificial intelligence research in its early days.
However this approach sometimes labeled as Good Old Fashioned Artificial Intelligence (GOFAI) has 
shown its limits in terms of practicality. In these systems, a gigantic number of axioms and 
definitions is needed to arrive at a conclusion in all but the most basic of practical cases.
In recent years, AI has experienced a resurgence of interest, due to availability of data and
hardware and using non-deductive methods (neural networks, statistical inference). Of course the
decisions we arrive at using these methods aren’t as clean-cut as when using a formal system. And as
we design machines with higher and higher power of abstraction, it is important to remember, we just
can’t know everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hilp&quot;&gt;Hilbert, D. (1900). Mathematical Problems. &lt;i&gt;BULLETIN OF THE AMERICAN MATHEMATICAL SOCIETY&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;sep-proof-theory-development&quot;&gt;von Plato, J. (2018). The Development of Proof Theory. In E. N. Zalta (Ed.), &lt;i&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/i&gt; (Winter 2018). Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;sep-goedel-incompleteness&quot;&gt;Raatikainen, P. (2018). Gödel’s Incompleteness Theorems. In E. N. Zalta (Ed.), &lt;i&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/i&gt; (Fall 2018). Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;nissanke1999introductory&quot;&gt;Nissanke, N. (1999). &lt;i&gt;Introductory Logic and Sets for Computer Scientists&lt;/i&gt;. Addison Wesley Longman.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hopcroft&quot;&gt;Hopcroft, J. E., Motwani, R., &amp;amp; Ullman, J. D. (2006). &lt;i&gt;Introduction to Automata Theory, Languages, and Computation (3rd Edition)&lt;/i&gt;. Boston, MA, USA: Addison-Wesley Longman Publishing Co., Inc.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the sake of brevity, we’ll have to take the existence of that formula as given &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

        
        
        
        
        

        

        

        
        <category term="maths" />
        

        
        <summary type="html">For millenia, people have needed a way to discover truth and knowledge about the world. The process was plagued by sophistry and inaccuracies before Aristotle gathered his thoughts on the matter in a series of works named The Organon (translated as “The Instrument”). Since then logic has played a central part in the development of Science and Mathematics, and is still used informally in everyday life to decide what is right or wrong.</summary>
        

        
        
    </entry>
    
    
</feed>
